[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is a a quote from a Ajahn Annāmalai Thera, you might know.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, keep a watchful eye on the gateway, not acting out of pressure that endures on any level, regardless of how long it endures.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what will make you an island for yourself, make you an island for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just to recap, to go through it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the gateway that one must be guarding?
[SPEAKER_01]: Correctly established mindfulness on that peripheral level, for which
[SPEAKER_01]: Virtue and sense restraint are necessary prerequisites.
[SPEAKER_01]: As we said in previous talks, you won't even see.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't even know how to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will not appear for you, the, you know, the domain of the peripheral, unless your behavior has been purified beforehand, unless you have been cultivating virtue and sense restraint and watchfulness and being moderate in eating and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when you
[SPEAKER_01]: When you try to apply this, like, okay, I'll learn how to... well, I'll learn how to recognize what's also there, in my experience, right here, right now, such as this body, for example, without needing to look at it, to know that it's there, because you already know that it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, how would you know what to look for?
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the dependence on that direct seeing as a measure of existence,
[SPEAKER_01]: And putting that peripheral knowledge of what's already there existing, second.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's learning how to reverse that order, fix it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do that, you guide that, that's the gateway.
[SPEAKER_01]: That right order, right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, okay, so you're guiding that right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in a way that you said that the gate, the gateway,
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that mental choosing to engage with unwholesome things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, yeah, perspective for your choice is the perspective of the right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the right order is the gateway.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you choose whether to pervert the order and give in to the pressure and, you know, put the second as first.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example,
[SPEAKER_01]: You mindful of the body correctly on the peripheral level, as the gateway, your virtue has been cultivated beforehand and so on, and now you have, you know, some doubts about some things regarding the body, regarding this, but all of that, all of those doubts, mental states, hindrances, pressures, are within the body enduring there on the peripheral level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is never a reason to abandon that and put it second and prioritize that which doubt presented you with.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's choosing to abandon the gateway when you choose to accept what doubt presented you with.
[SPEAKER_01]: You walk away from it and that's the whole point of doubt as a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the whole... the whole trick of it is just to get you to walk away from your post.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you can never... that's why the right answers will never satisfy that doubt, because there was never a point.
[SPEAKER_01]: There was just a pretext.
[SPEAKER_01]: But unless you're able to withstand the pressure of the doubt and sustain the right order in face of it, you will not be able to endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you see, whatever hindrance will arise, it all arises within.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hindrance tries to throw you off, pressure you, pull you, scare you, frighten you, all these things, just so you abandon the post of the right order, just so you drop, or obscure, or walk away from the recognition of peripherally enduring body there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it makes you engage with...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not making you engage.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pressuring you to, and you choose to, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you are responsible for the... if hindrances hinder you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not responsible for hindrances arising, but you're responsible if you're hindered by them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it means like, oh, you accepted the order that they were pressuring you for.
[SPEAKER_01]: You acted out of them, in other words.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see that order, correct?
[SPEAKER_01]: You endure the order in face of the pressure of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you go surmount the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Surmounting the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not resolving them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not finding the right answers for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But isn't it... you see a hindrance there, pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can also see that you can choose to engage with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can choose to give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you see the power of your choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: The power you have there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can either give in or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but that power of your choice, it's not rooted just in, like, the you or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's rooted in the options.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that option is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the option is to stay at the gateway and not prioritize the hindrance or to prioritize the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, what's really the power there?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the knowledge behind it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, the choice is a form of power.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: What to do?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't know, you must stay at the gateway, despite all the pressure, despite all the unnatural feeling of it, because it feels just much more natural and satisfying to address this and fix it and sort it, this pressure of the doubt or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But unless you have thoroughly understood that, no, that's a trap, you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't accidentally or spontaneously choose to guard the right order and become a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to understand the value through pondering on it beforehand and then stick to it and endure it against the grain, against the pull.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter what the world's telling you, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, whatever the world's telling you, you have a reference point now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if what the world's telling you is according to the right order, you say, okay, the world is right in this instance.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the world is telling you the opposite, you say, no, the world is wrong in this instance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... so that, again, guarding, you say, you're saying, guarding that gateway, is not letting those hindrances in, not engaging with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's really not engaging with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not engaging.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because letting them in might be misconstrued.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know what you mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know what I meant, probably, if I said it before,
[SPEAKER_01]: It might be misconstrued, like, oh, I must prevent them from coming to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: They arise, they come to the doorstep, you just don't let them in.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you let them in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you welcome them, you delight in them, you accept them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at the same time, as I said so many times before, you don't try to chase them away either, because that would also require you to abandon your post at the very threshold of the gateway.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to go out and start chasing them and so on, which means, you know, you turn your back to that which you should have guarded.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, endure the pressure to let them in, if they are agreeable, and endure the pull to chase them away, if they are disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And endure the pull to ignore them, if they are neither.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because look, they're not trying to come in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I can snooze at the post.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, they're not trying to come in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have to endure the the pull of chasing them away and the pressure of trying to... of them trying to get in, but I certainly should not go to sleep either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's... it's relaxing when they're not trying to get in and they're just sitting there, but at the same time,
[SPEAKER_01]: I shouldn't be too relaxed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where there's the subtlest, the neutral feeling that basically needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's just so easy to become indolent and careless about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Complacent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Distracted from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, vigilant in times of calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Vigilant in times of calm and then persistent in the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's the
[SPEAKER_01]: pressure to welcome it, you persist in not doing so.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's the pull to take you, pull you out, to chase them away, if they're un... un... un... if they're disagreeable, you also have to persist in that, enduring that pull.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, see, that that's a wrong question, because it already implies that you start engaged.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start pressured or pulled, but that's not the engagement.
[SPEAKER_01]: The engagement is what you do on account of that pressure that you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is to not act out of that feeling and develop sufficient mindfulness in regard to it peripherally and endure it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, and also see the value in doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, that needs to come beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't start doing this without still doubting the value of doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this kind of question comes up...
[SPEAKER_01]: People understand this.
[SPEAKER_01]: People are pressured by the pain, but they want the answer to get rid of the pain, which means they keep doing the same thing, acting out of pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the gradual training is there, repeated so many times in the suttas and in our talks.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, virtue is the first, guarding of the sense doors, sense restraint, moderation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the doubt that comes, well, restrain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the point to find the satisfying answer over and over and over again.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is to endure the non-answering on the basis of your virtue and mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you just give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: You build this up, you're coming near the gateway, and then you just run out, chasing the answers and so on, and forget where you should have stopped and protected it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it keeps coming up, because people are impatient.
[SPEAKER_01]: You always want someone to tell you what you must do, but they tell you what to do, so... And then you want to be told again what you need to do, because the satisfaction of the answer has run out, and the principle of acting out of pressure or the pull hasn't diminished, hasn't changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still act out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't practiced that yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't practiced that.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you've been doing is acting out and finding answers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which, you have to start with.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, the point comes when you have sufficient amount of answers.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have sufficient amount of information.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you need to start applying it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And enduring that doubt, that's going to become more and more irrational, the more you don't give in to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it's going to be more and more pressuring, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you have the virtue, you have the sense restraint, got it, and you endure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it will have to calm down.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind will have to calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I was reading about the development of the perception of abandoning.
[SPEAKER_00]: That kind of perception must be developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's pretty much similar to what you're saying here.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just read it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And which is the perception of
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is called the perception of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and that's often, see,
[SPEAKER_01]: People read just that, and mean like, oh, I must prevent these things from arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I must get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, these thoughts come, and I must have them not come.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the result of it is, you abandon the gateway, you abandon the mindfulness, you abandon the right order, and you welcome, and you engage, and you start fighting or chasing
[SPEAKER_01]: which is what they wanted you to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wanted you to abandon the gateway and accept them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to try to abandon thoughts, you actually accepted them and abandoned that which you shouldn't have abandoned, which is the right order of your right mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, you can understand abandonment to mean that, but you can also understand abandonment to mean what we are saying it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you abandon the thoughts, you abandon these wild animals, they will stop coming to you if you stop feeding them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's endless.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start chasing them and killing them one by one, they keep popping back up.
[SPEAKER_01]: New ones.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't, you know, you can cancel the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is that now?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're free from thoughts forever?
[SPEAKER_01]: You're free from underlying currency of like the pressuring feeling in regard?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing has changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just got rid of the specific thought that bothered you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, after the abandonment, or if you understand the abandonment the way I'm describing it, then you realize, okay, so you actually unplug, uproot, remove that fuel for these thoughts to come back.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, yeah, you abandon them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And not just one instance of it, but now they stop coming.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're no longer feeding them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, because you stop feeding them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, by not welcoming, you will abandon them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how monks skillfully abandon these thoughts and abandon their unskillful states.
[SPEAKER_00]: But particularly this last point, he does not give in to the continual arising of evil.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because it'll stop coming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they are continually arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're continually arising, he's not giving in, the order is not compromised, the right order, the mindfulness established on the body peripherally correctly, that gateway is not abandoned, doesn't matter how continually these thoughts arise, this does not change.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the arahant... well, the one who practices is steadfast in that, and, you know, it basically... it becomes fortified in that right order.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more that's developed, the less and less these thoughts will be coming, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: There will be fewer and fewer and fewer, and the pressure will be fading away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because each time you abandon the gateway, you engage with the thoughts, which means that's what they feed on.
[SPEAKER_01]: They see they can move you, they'll keep coming to try and move you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if after a sufficient amount of time, the order hasn't moved, they will basically drift away, lose interest and walk away, see that they've been wasting their time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in this last thing, he doesn't give in to the continual arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma is saying...
[SPEAKER_00]: Continuously, right, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's exactly what happens, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're still engaging with the thoughts individually and, you know, trying to chase them away, get rid of them, when it's one or two, you do it successfully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, exactly, three or four, you can't keep up
[SPEAKER_01]: 15, 16, oh, you're done.
[SPEAKER_01]: If that was the only way of abandonment that you knew, get rid of, get rid of, get rid of, you'll be overwhelmed, overrun, quickly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that might work for one thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly why people struggle, because it kind of works initially, and they think, oh, so that's the abandonment they must do, but they don't realize that abandonment that you must do is basically on the level of fortifying where you stand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fighting more and more thoughts at the same time, because that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's going to run out.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically going to be exhausting, and you're going to be run over.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be fortified to that, no matter how...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is one thought, and you can just ignore it, of the unwholesome kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, abandon it in their way, but don't confuse that for the uprooting of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, I don't want to think about this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's fine if it works, but the time will come when that will not work.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if there's the only way of abandoning that you knew,
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to be overrun, they'll be inside, you'll be running out, the gateway is gone, destroyed, you know, precepts compromised, and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to... people have to basically broaden the understanding of what abandonment is, and certainly stop conflating it with, I must stop thinking and get rid of this, because even the thought of abandoning this particular thought, is another thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, thinking that you must stop thinking,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not abandonment at all, and it's actually a contradiction in terms, which means, as such, it's quite a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And often you see that in Buddhist meditations and traditions of how to stop thinking, stop thinking, focus now, feel the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of these focusing and feeling and stuff are thoughts, are perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, here you are believing you could stop your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not just that that's not the abandonment, you're actually kind of not even seeing the nature of that which is in front of your gate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're completely confused about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think it's not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think it's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: These thoughts are gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind is empty of thoughts, which is another thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to see the thoughts are always being there, and the only way you can do is protect the gateway in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if there are no thoughts, evil, unwholesome thoughts, you're still developing and keeping that perception of abandoning there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what would that keeping be?
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be sustaining of the order.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said before, sustaining of the right order, peripheral mindfulness of the body being there,
[SPEAKER_01]: means everything else that you're experiencing within that, is going to be experienced in a detached manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, whatever feeling he feels, he feels it detached.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's that's exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You protect that, that's the abandonment of any attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abandonment on any base for passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sustain it until the greed, aversion, delusion and any traces of it completely evaporate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that confusing, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that confusing, obviously, but exactly that's the point, because it is the right practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: The closer you get to it, the more will your mind try to throw from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Mahārāja is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your own mind is the, you know, an assassin that pretends to be a friend, as the sūtas say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the more you start doing it rightly, the stronger the doubts will be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, the more of the fortifying
[SPEAKER_01]: of the right order you have to do and sustain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or faith you have to have.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That basic reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the faith is kind of prerequisite, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, you know, you could see that perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those unwholesome things, I don't have to choose them.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to engage with those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you abandon them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, so I don't have to do anything, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't have to go out of my way to abandon them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just have to stay here and not go anyway, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they will be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not being given attention to, and acted out of, and welcomed, and delighted, and engaged, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Encouraged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Encouraged, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not invited.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not invited, all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's difficult to do, obviously, because it's a very simple thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because that's basically now on the level of enduring it mentally, that discomfort of that... You know, waiting.
[SPEAKER_01]: Waiting, patience in front of you, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Trying to pressure you, trying to convince you, oh, do this, do that, let them in, go out, or just one slip, you get careless, oh, oh, that's it, that's it, you acted out.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that's that's the pain of the practice, but pain of the development.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you take it on, that's also the pain that results in uprooting of any basis for pain in the future.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not just managing anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then another thought comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, so I have to chase it away again, which means I'm not really free.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm pressured by the duty of having to chase it away, having to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then too many thoughts come, and you can't deal with it, because you only knew how to deal with individual thoughts, by kind of addressing them, changing them, chasing them away.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, management will never result in freedom, only in postponing the obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you are still equally pressured.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as you said, as I said in that quote, it is what will make you an island for yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consistent vigilance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely, basically, self-sufficient internally, contained, detached.
[SPEAKER_00]: Highlands detached from any other.
[SPEAKER_00]: From the beginning, it's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fortifying the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's exactly the gist of every gradual training that the Buddha described, which is always the same gradual training.
[SPEAKER_01]: But every instance he described, it's always the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take it on, do this, do this, do this, and then dwell in these states, and protect these states, and so on, and there's only one outcome.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be an island to yourself.